So these kinds of problems this is a very,
very simplified version of
what are called in the statistics literature
as bandit problems.
Do you know why they are called bandit problems
you know this, Deepak no, oh come on you have
attended enough of lab meetings to know these
things anyway so people know what a one-armed
bandit is come on man anyway so one-armed
bandit is a slot machine, you know what slot
machines are you put a coin there then you
pull a lever right, and then what it does
it steals your money basically I mean all
of that is mumbo jumbo you know of course
all of you must realize that no casino is
going to put up a machine that actually makes
money for the customer, right.
So in the long run the slot machine will steal
your money right and then you just keep pulling
that thing so that lever that you pull is
called the arm right and since it has one
lever it is called the one-armed bandit because
it steals your money so this is one arm bandit.
So here this is very similar to the slot machine
except that instead of having one arm it has
n arms, right so each time you pull an arm
you get some kind of a pay off right and if
you want to really complete the Bandit analogy.
So every time you need to pull an arm you
have to pay one rupee, right sometimes you
get back one rupee sometimes you get back
nothing so that way you know that it is certainly
stealing your money it is something like that,
right.
So but that is essentially why it is called
a bandit problem sometimes it is also called
the multi armed bandits, right so it is called
multi armed bandits because well it has multiple
arms right and the dynamics is very similar
to a slot machine, right.
Now we know why I kept calling actions as
arms, right so because the literature typically
talks about arms on a bandit right, but it
is really for us we do not have to worry about
the Bandit connections so then it is essentially
just actions, right good any questions so
far.
There are many, many ways in which you can
solve this multi-armed bandit problems right,
but the crux here is always that you'll have
to be balancing the exploration versus exploitation,
right.
So I will talk about multiple solution concepts
right, what do we mean when we say I want
to solve a multi-armed bandit problem, right.
So one solution concept, right is asymptotic
correctness so what do I mean by that I do
not put any bounds on you or anything right
here is this multi-armed bandit problem so
give me a guarantee that eventually you will
be selecting the arm which has the highest
payoff, right as t tends to infinity you will
be selecting the arm that has the highest
payoff so that is called asymptotic correctness,
right.
So this is one way of solving it a lot of
the older literature on bandit problems essentially
concern themselves with asymptotic correctness
and then of course they had some results on
things like rates of convergence and so on
so forth how quickly you reach the guarantee
and so on so forth, but by and large the analysis
was on asymptotic correctness they come up
with very simple algorithms and then you show
that the asymptotically they will converge
to the right arm, right.
So this is a one kind of thing right, the
second popular solution concept is essentially
known as regret optimality suppose I knew
okay, suppose I knew from time 0 which is
the best arm right, suppose I knew from the
beginning what is the best term to pull right
and I keep pulling the arm over and over and
over again right and I keep repeating this
experiment multiple times what will be my
expected payoff?
so this is time, expected payoff it’s going
to be some kind of a flat line, right.
So that is possibly the best expected payoff
that I can achieve right because I know from
the beginning I know what is the right arm,
right but since I do not know this I have
to do this exploration, right to figure out
which is the right arm right so my payoff
will look something like this right, over
time it will and eventually reach that right
as time becomes I mean when T goes to infinity
I will eventually reach that point, right.
So now this reward that you see here right,
this is what I could have got if I had known
the right answer from the beginning, right
so this is in some sense a loss that I incurred
because of my learning process right, so this
is sometimes colorfully referred to as regret
so it’s like oh alas if I had known this
from the beginning you know I could have done
so much better so this is regret.
So another way of thinking about regret is
that I am trying to maximize the total reward
that I obtained okay, not just the asymptotically
the payoff right, even during the learning
I need to get as much pay off as possible
right.
So ideally I would want this slope to be pretty
steep right, if the slope is very steep so
what will happen is this area will come down
right, if the slope is very steep this area
is going to come down.
But what is the trade-off typically you will
have to give up is it will take a longer time
to reach optimality usually there is a trade-off
right, because you typically to do this right
you will be giving up some amount of exploration
right, so there are some corner cases where
you might actually miss out on important exploration
because you are trying to be very optimistic
with respect to this regret thing right so
I want it to be I want to have very little
regret so what my what I might end up doing
is I might miss out on certain key exploration
that I should have done.
So essentially what will happen is so in some
cases I will never reach optimality also because
I would have ignored certain important outcomes
along the way so this is the trade-off that
you have to worry about.
But regret optimality is essentially looking
at how steeply you learn at the outset okay
of course that does not mean I can be really
bad right I mean does it have a small regret
right, but I did learn very fast I actually
went up the y-axis right but then I am going
to incur a constant very, very large constant
regret okay.
So that is not so you have to balance it right,
so because you keep accumulating even though
this is reached here but you still keep accumulating
regret right, so it is not yet come to the
optimal case in fact we know that no algorithm
can guarantee that your regret will grow small,
I mean essentially regret will fall right,
faster than log t so it has to grow at least
as log t right, suppose you have taken t times
steps the regret you have accumulated till
that point will be proportional to log t,
right.
So and as t becomes larger the rate of growth
will become smaller and smaller right but
that is the best rate of growth that you can
achieve all that you can fiddle play around
with this some A times log t will be the rate
right, so that A is what you can fiddle around
with so those constants you can fiddle around
with but log t itself is non-negotiable so
there are results that show that log t is
a lower bound so you can’t do better than
log t in achieving regret, right.
So the essentially so if you think of this
area above this curve and between this dotted
line in this curve so that area will keep
growing at some rate right, as t becomes larger
and larger that area keeps growing at some
rate so the rate at which it will grow will
be at least log t, so that is the result that
we have, so I am not going to show you that
result but will talk about a couple of other
things okay, so is it clear so people understand
what regret is right, good.
So third thing that I want to talk about is
what is called
PAC optimality right, or not is not I should
not say we call it PAC optimality but it should
be more of a PAC complexity right, so it is
a little tricky thing.
So PAC stands for probably approximately correct,
okay sometimes in a very loose fashion we
tend to use these as interchangeable things
yeah, he probably right and he is approximately
right, right so but they are not interchangeable
in the very different context very, very different
things and when I say somebody is probably
right that means he is either right or wrong
okay, so he is right with some probability
and he is wrong with some probability right.
When I say somebody is approximately right
is almost surely not right, right but he is
very close to being right this is essentially
what approximately means, so it turns out
that both of these concepts are applicable
in the Bandit setting.
So when I say somebody is approximately right
in the Bandit setting what do I mean that
I give you an arm right, finally you know
what is the goal at the end of the day I am
supposed to give you an arm back, right and
this is supposed to have the highest expected
payoff.
When I say I am approximately right that means
that arm I am going to return to you will
be very close in pay off to the best possible
arm, right.
Suppose I return some a to you so q star of
a will be very close to say q star of a star
which is the best arm, right does is it make
sense so I will return some arm a to you at
the end of my algorithm q star of a will be
very, very close to q star of a star right
what is q star again the true expected payoff
which I do not know about right, the algorithm
does not know what q star is but it will return
an arm and the guarantee I give you is the
q star of that arm the unknown q star of the
top will be close to the q star of the best
arm, okay this is the approximately correct
okay.
So what is the probably correct part here,
no, it is either approximately correct or
not, because we already only giving you approximately
correct guarantees right, so with a very high
probability it is approximately correct, right
with some small probability it might give
you an arm that is more than some distance
away from the best arm yeah that is what PAC
is probably approximately correct.
Oh, I say okay, probably correct would mean
yeah either optimal or not optimal yeah probably
approximately correct is well with some probability
you are approximately correct some probability
you are not, right so typically there are
many ways in which people talk about this
there is a 1 popular way of specifying this
is called the epsilon delta PAC where epsilon
refers to the approximately part and the Delta
refers to the probability part right.
So with probability of 1- delta okay, the
solution I return to you will be within epsilon
of the best arm right, so this essentially
means probability that probability that q
star of a that is the arm returned to you
is greater than… that is one way of writing
it but that is not what the PAC framework
guarantees, okay.
So what was the difference between the first
one and this one that is the first one was
relative guarantee this one is an absolute
guarantee, so you could think of either way
you can think of absolute guarantee or as
a relative guarantee but this is essentially
what PAC optimality means right, so for a
given epsilon delta if I can give that guarantee
right then I say it is PAC optimal for this.
But what is the interesting part here right,
if I allow you to draw an infinite number
of samples from the arms right, I can always
guarantee this right given give me whatever
epsilon delta I want i can just keep drawing
arms okay, and then at some point I can say
okay now I have satisfied this okay.
The optimality part comes in when you want
to minimize the sample complexity right, so
given an epsilon and a Delta what is the smallest
number of times I have to select arms such
that I can give you that epsilon delta PAC
guarantee right, does it make sense.
So that is essentially what we are looking
at here, so this is a sample complexity question
right this is a the correctness question right,
this is a kind of rate of convergence question
and this is a sample complexity equation so
these are all slightly different notions of
solutions when I say you are solving a bandit
problem these are different notions of solutions
and the kind of algorithms that you come up
with for addressing each of these questions
would be pretty different.
You do not know but I give you the guarantee
this is the, if you know q star of a star
then this will be as close as that.
Exactly so these are questions that we will
look at as we go along I have not told you
what I am just telling you what the solution
concepts are right I have not even told you
how you actually solve these problems right
so when we look at those I will tell you how
to go about doing this.
In fact it will turn out that the algorithms
themselves are very simple okay, but to analyze
it to show that this kind of guarantee holds
is where all that trick lies.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved